Guide to the James D. Shaw Papers, 1827-1896 AIS.1968.08
ULS Archives & Special Collections
James D. Shaw Papers
1827-1896
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Shaw, James D.
AIS.1968.08
1.88 Linear Feet (3 Boxes)
James D. Shaw was a small business entrepreneur who was engaged in the lumbering business in Western Pennsylvania and newspaper publishing in West Virginia. Shaw's papers consist primarily of business records and correspondence from 1860-1893 relating to the lumbering business. The collection also contains documents relating to his office of Justice of the Peace, Tyler County, West Virginia, 1889-91.
Biography
James D. Shaw was a small business entrepreneur in Western Pennsylvania and West Virginia during the last half of the 19th century. In the 1870's, Shaw engaged in the lumber business and was a partner in Hahn and Shaw, manufacturer of all kinds of rough and dressed lumber, at Blairs Corners, Clarion County, Pennsylvania. While in Western Pennsylvania, he served as board secretary of the Beaver Township School District.
During the 1880's, Shaw moved to West Virginia where he founded the newspaper West Virginia Echo at Middlebourne in Tyler County. The newspaper remained here for only a short time and then was removed to Moundsville, West Virginia, and renamed the Moundsville Echo. Shaw continued to operate the Moundsville Echo until his death in 1917.
Shaw served as a Justice of the Peace in Tyler County, West Virginia, from 1889-1891.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers of James D. Shaw provide a history of the lumbering industry in Western Pennsylvania during the 19th century. The collection consists primarily of business records relating to the Hahn and Shaw lumber company from 1867-1892. These records include bills, orders, receipts, and business correspondence. For many of these years, ledgers and account books were kept that described the workings of a lumber company. The account books in Box 3, folders 36-38 are both ledgers and daybooks of the Hahn and Shaw Lumber Company that include time records, expenses, and lumber sales for the years 1872-1889. The ledgers in Box 1 and 2 pertain only to the Hahn and Shaw Lumber Company while the ledgers in Box 4 include some personal and boarding account information.
The collection also describes newspaper publishing in West Virginia in the late 19th century. The records of the West Virginia Echo and the Moundsville Echo mostly include correspondence between publishers which can be found in folder 2. A ledger for the years 1877-1888 can be found in folder 8 that contains some financial information about the newspaper business. In addition, legal papers relating to the West Virginia Echo and the Moundsville Echo from 1889-1896 can be found in folder 18.
Also included in the collection are the legal papers of James D. Shaw for the years 1880-1892. These papers are in folder 15 and include legal judgment, summons, oil leases, agreement on right to cut timber and saw logs, house lease, and agreement conferring right to act in selling same land. The papers relating to Beaver Township School District are in folder 16, which contains vouchers, receipts, and contracts from when he served as board secretary from 1877-1879. James D. Shaw's appointment as Justice of the Peace, Tyler County, West Virginia from 1889 to 1891 is documented in legal papers held in folder 17 and associated costs can be found in the ledger in folder 8. The legal papers include correspondence (1888-1891); court writs (1890-1891); affidavits (1889-1991); subpoenas (1889-1890); sheriff's receipts; and Justice of the Peace fees.
The Tonkin Family Papers (ais 63:3) is a related collection that may be of interest to researchers of the lumbering industry in Western Pennsylvania during the 19th century.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Sam J. Shaw, April 30, 1968.
Previous Citation
James D. Shaw Papers, 1827-1896, AIS.1968.08, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Shaw, James D., Papers, 1827-1896, ais 68:8, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Businessmen -- Pennsylvania; Publishers and publishing -- West Virginia; Lumbering -- Pennsylvania -- History; Newspaper publishing -- West Virginia -- History; Justices of the peace -- West Virginia -- Tyler County; Pennsylvania -- History; West Virginia -- History; Personal papers; Politics; Business and Industry; Shaw, James D.
- Business Correspondence, (intermittent), 1871-1883 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Memorandum Notebooks, 18 volumes, 1882-1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Note Calculation, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Promissory Notes, 1875-1890 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bills, 1869-1894 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Ledger, 1869-1875 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Ledger, 1877-1888 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ledger, 1870-1879 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Business Statements, 1871-1893 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Business Receipts, 1870-1895 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Tax Receipts, (intermittent), 1876-1893 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Certificate of Shareholder, Savings and Loan Association, Minneapolis, Minnesota, July 10, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Time Books, 3 volumes, 1877-1881, 1893, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Legal Papers, 1880-1892 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Papers, Beaver Township School District, 1877-1879 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Papers, Justice of the Peace, Tyler County, West Virginia, 1889-1891 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Papers, West Virginia Echo and Moundsville Echo, 1889-1896 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Papers, miscellaneous, 1877-1893 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Letter to Hahn and Shaw, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Journal Pages, Hahn and Shaw, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Ledger Pages, Hahn and Shaw, 1870, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Orders, Hahn and Shaw, 1871-1879 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Sales Books, Hahn and Shaw, 2 volumes, 1874-1896, 1877-1878 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Receipts, Hahn and Shaw, 1870-1879 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Delivery Receipts, Wilson and Greenland to Hahn and Shaw, 1877-1878 (Box 3, Folder 26-28)
- Bills, Hahn and Shaw, 1877-1878 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Statements, Hahn and Shaw, 1876-1878 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Deposit Slips, Hahn and Shaw, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Orders, Hahn and Shaw, 1876-1878 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Shaw, Hannah J., Release of Deed of Trust from J. D. Shaw to Hannah J. Shaw, 1879 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Shaw, David G., Cloth Drying Directions, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Davis, Thomas and John, Tax Receipts, (intermittant), 1827-1841 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Account Book, 1872-1875 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Account Book, 1876-1880 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Account Book, 1882-1889 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Ledgers, miscellaneous, 7 volumes, (intermittant), 1867-1885 (Box 4)